曾經有個人
Once there was a man
想要找出地球的真實年齡
who went searching for the true age of the earth.
經過他的努力
In his struggles to discover it,
他無意間發現了一個極大的威脅
he stumbled on a grave threat.
1966年 加州 帕薩迪納 春季的某一天
Beautiful spring day, Pasadena, California. 1966.
人們安居樂業
Business is booming, life's good.
只有一個人
Except for one man,
名叫克萊爾·彼得森的地質化學家
a geochemist named Clair Patterson,
朋友叫他派特
known as Pat.
他認為他所看到的所有人都身處於無形的威脅中
He knows that everyone he sees is in danger from an invisible menace.
他決心要阻止這一切
And he's determined to put a stop to it,
不計代價
no matter what the cost.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第七集
為了要說清楚彼得森的故事
You can't really tell Pat Patterson's story
必須要從很久很久以前地球誕生前說起
without going all the way back to the time long before the earth our home, was built,
那時星星剛剛產生它的物質
when the stars brought forth its substance.
鐵
Iron
帶來了行星的熾熱內核
For the planet's molten core.
氧
Oxygen.
帶來了岩石 水和空氣
For the rocks and the water and the air.
碳
Carbon.
帶來了鑽石和生命
For diamonds. And life.
一顆星誕生了
A star is born,
我們的星球
ours.
最初的幾百萬年裏 一切還算順利
For the first few million years, things ran smoothly
塵土顆粒滾雪球般的逐漸變成更大的物體
as dust grains snowballed into progressively larger objects.
直到這個物體大到一定程度
But once these objects grew massive enough
有了足夠的引力
to have sufficient gravity,
它們開始相互吸引 從而軌道相交相撞
they began pulling each other into crossing orbits.
這就是我們的世界最初的模樣
This is how our world looked when it was new.
地球表面沒有地方可以倖免於難
No part of the earth's surface could survive intact
一直到現在
from that time to the present.
既然地球的幼年記錄都不復存在了
So, with all its birth and early childhood records erased,
我們怎麼才能確定地球真正的年紀呢
how could we ever hope to know with any certainty the true age of our world?
這是個自古以來的謎
People have been wondering about this since antiquity.
1650年 愛爾蘭大主教詹姆斯·烏捨爾
In 1650 archbishop James Ussher of Ireland
得出一個貌似正確的結論
made a calculation that seemed to settle the question.
就和當時大多數人一樣
Like almost everyone else of his time and his world,
他的根據是聖經的造物論
he accepted the biblical account of creation as authoritative.
但是聖經裏也沒有提到具體的年代
But the Bible does not give exact years,
於是烏捨爾在舊約中尋找一個
so Ussher searched for an event in the Old Testament
與已知歷史事件相吻合的時間
that corresponded to a known historical date.
他在列王記下卷中發現了
He found it in the second book of kings,
巴比倫統治者尼布甲尼撒二世死於公元前562年
the death of the Babylonian ruler Nebuchadnezzar in 562 B.C.
烏捨爾將世代的先知和族長加起來
Usher added up the generations of the prophets and the Patriarchs,
舊約中的139個族譜
the 139 "Begats" of the Old Testament,
從亞當一直到尼布甲尼撒二世
between Adam and the time of Nebuchadnezzar,
他發現
and discovered
這個世界誕生於10月22號
that the world began on October 22
公元前4004年
in the year 4004 B.C.
下午六點
At 6:00 P.M.
星期六
It was a Saturday.
烏捨爾大主教制定的年表在當時的西方被奉為真理
Archbishop Ussher's chronology was taken as gospel in the Western world.
直到我們通過另一種途徑瞭解地球的年紀
Until we turned to another book to find the age of the earth,
通過研究岩石本身的記錄
the one that was written in the rocks themselves.
科羅拉多大峽谷中大多數的岩層
Most of the rock layers in the walls of the Grand Canyon
都屬於沉積岩 由許多細小的顆粒堆積而成
are made of sediments, deposited as fine grains
這些沉積岩形成的時候 這裏還是海洋
in a time when this part of the world was a sea.
年復一年 沉積物被不斷增加的新沉積物壓縮成了岩石
Over eons, the sediments were compressed into rock under the weight of succeeding layers,
最下面的就是最古老的
with the oldest ones at the bottom.
隨便選一層
Pick a layer, any layer.
那個怎麼樣
How about that one?
很久以前 這裏水並不深
Once upon a time, there must have been shallow water here.
在前寒武紀時期
Back in the Precambrian period,
大約10億年前
about a billion years ago,
那時只有一種生物
there was only one kind of life.
這些藍綠色的細菌忙著收穫陽光
These blue-green bacteria were busy harvesting sunlight
從而產生氧氣
and making oxygen.
對他們來說那只是廢氣
For them, it was just a waste product,
但對於後來的動物 包括我們來說
but for the animals who evolved later, including us,
那是孕育生命的呼吸
it was the breath of life.
另選一層
Okay. Pick another layer.
那個怎麼樣
How about that one?
這層被稱為光明天使頁岩
This layer is known as the bright angel shale.
形成於5.3億年前
It formed about 530 million years ago.
這些足跡屬於2.6億年前
These tracks were left 260 million years ago.
你想知道地球的年紀
So you want to know the age of the earth?
只要瞭解形成每一層所需的時間
Just figure out how long it took to deposit each layer
不需要把族譜加起來
and then, instead of counting the "Begats,"
把這些層次加起來就夠了
add up all the layers.
很簡單吧
Easy, right?
還有一個問題 我們是根據觀察這個過程得出的結論
Just one problem, We know from observing this process,
因為它還在持續
because it still happens today
在海洋中 在湖泊中
in oceans and lakes around the world.
沉積層的形成時間長度各不相同
That sediments can be laid down at widely different rates.
通常都是非常的緩慢
It usually happens very slowly,
大約1000年才有1英尺
say a foot of sediment per 1,000 years.
但如果發生了罕見的大洪災
But when the's a rare catastrophic flood,
速度就會快很多
it can happen much faster,
幾天就已經有1英尺了
as much as a foot in just a few days.
許多地質學家嘗試用這種方式來計算地球的年紀
Many geologists tried this method to calculate the age of the earth.
他們勘探了大峽谷
They used the Grand Canyon
還有地球上其他的沉積層區域
and other sedimentary sequences around the planet.
但是他們的結論差異卻無法統一
But their answers ranged too widely to be of much use,
差異範圍從300萬年到150億年
anywhere between three million years and 15 billion.
這個方法還有其他的問題
And there were other problems with this method:
即使最下層的岩石
Even the deepest layers of rock
也不是地球上最古老的東西
are not the oldest things on earth.
因為即使岩石也不能從地球最初所受的災難中倖存
Why? Because not even rocks could survive the earth's violent infancy.
而太空 那又是另一回事
In space it's another story.
地球誕生時留下了任何的紀念品嗎
Are there any mementos from when the earth was born,
有可以證明真實年齡的物體嗎
objects that could possibly tell us its true age?
我知道一個地方 可以找到當年太陽系形成時
I know a place where the unused bricks and mortar left over
殘留的遺跡
from the creation of our solar system can be found.
它們存在於木星和火星的軌道間
It lies between the orbits of Jupiter and Mars.
這些是產生地球的原料
Here is the stuff of the newborn earth,
它們在冰冷的太空中飄蕩
adrift in cold storage, unchanged
從未改變過
ever since that time.
100萬年左右之前
A million or so years ago,
一顆大的小行星恰巧擊撞了一顆較小的
a large asteroid happened to jostle a much smaller one,
將它推到一個新的軌道
sending it on a new trajectory,
它的運動軌跡在大約5萬年前的一個夜晚終結
a collision course that ended one night some 50,000 years ago.
它從天空劃過打破了大峽谷的平靜
It must have shattered the peace of the Grand Canyon as it sailed overhead...
撞擊形成這個大坑
to blast out this crater
即大峽谷所在的州
在後來這裏被稱為 亞利桑那
in what would one day be known as Arizona.
這顆鐵質小行星的碎片
Fragments of the iron asteroid that made this crater
被完整的保留了下來
have survived intact.
如果我們知道這塊鐵的形成時間
If we just knew how long ago that iron was forged,
我們就能知道太陽系的年齡
we'd know the age of the solar system.
也包括地球
Including the earth.
怎麼才能知道呢
But how could we know that?
挑塊石頭
Pick a rock.
隨便一塊石頭
Any rock.
這個怎麼樣
How about that one?
這塊石頭中的某些原子可能具有放射性
Some atoms in this rock could be radioactive,
它們自然地發生衰變
which means they spontaneously disintegrate
從而變成其他元素
and become other elements.
鈾原子首先變成釷原子
A uranium atom first becomes a thorium atom.
平均而言 耗時十幾億年
On average, it takes a few billion years.
釷很不穩定
The thorium is much more unstable.
不到一個月的時間就能變成鏷
In less than a month it turns into protactinium.
一分鐘後 鏷又變成了其他元素
A minute later, protactinium becomes something else.
又經過10次的核轉變
The atom undergoes ten more nuclear transmutations...
來到衰變鏈的最後一環
Until it reaches the last stop on the decay chain:
衰變鏈指的是放射性衰變過程中成鏈產生的一系列衰變產物
一個穩定的鉛原子
A stable atom of lead.
鉛將不再發生變化
And lead it will remain... For eternity.
20世紀有個巨大的成就  在幾十年裏
In the 20th century there was a huge effort, lasting decades,
測量每種放射性元素轉變成另一種元素所用的時間後
to measure the time it takes for each radioactive element to transmute into another element.
物理學家發現每個不穩定元素的原子
Physicists discovered that the atoms of each unstable element
衰變比率是恆定的
decay at a constant rate.
原子的原子核就像一座聖殿
The nucleus of an atom is a kind of sanctuary,
無視震動和環境的改變
immune to the shocks and upheavals of its environment.
用錘子砸
Hit it with a hammer.
在油裏炸
Boil it in oil.
氣化它
Vaporize it.
原子鐘走的不緊不慢
The nuclear clock goes on ticking,
每一跳的時間都絕對標準
keeping an absolute standard of time
不論日月星辰的變化
that does not look to the sun and the stars.
要瞭解地球真實的年齡 沒有比測量鈾原子更好的辦法了
What better way to find the true age of the earth than with the uranium atom?
只要知道岩石中鈾衰變成鉛的比率
If you knew what fraction of the uranium in a rock had turned into lead,
就可以計算出岩石存在了多久
you could calculate how much time had passed since the rock was formed
但有個問題
But there's a problem.
形成之初的那些岩石
The rocks in the earth that were present when it was formed
都已不復存在
are no more.
或被壓碎了 或被融化了 或者被重塑了
They've all been crushed, melted, remade.
有個辦法可以計算出鉛的最初數量
There is a way to calculate the amount of lead that was present from the beginning.
天賜的禮物
It's a gift from the heavens:
隕石
Meteorites.
這塊碎片來自造成這個大坑的隕石 很理想
This one... A fragment of the one that made this giant crater... Was ideal
這塊隕石中鉛的含量
The amount of lead deep inside this meteorite
與地球形成時的完全一樣
is exactly the same as when earth formed.
既然知道了鈾衰變的固定比率
Since you know the constant rate of uranium decay,
就可以知道這塊隕石的年齡
that should give you the age of the meteorite,
和地球的年齡一樣
which was made at the same time as the earth.
只要測量
All you had to do was measure
隕石中的鉛就行了
the amount of lead in meteorites.
很簡單吧
Easy, right?
一位在芝加哥大學名叫哈理森·布朗的科學家
A scientist named Harrison Brown at the University of Chicago,
1947年首次掌握了這個方法
first understood this in 1947.
他選擇了一位研究生來實際操作 克萊爾·彼得森
He chose a young graduate student, Clair Patterson, to do the work.
當時彼得森怎麼也不會想到這個作業
Patterson couldn't possibly know how this assignment
會改變他的一生
would alter the course of his life...
還有這個世界
And ours.
表面上只是單純的科學研究
What seemed like pure scientific research
結果卻不簡單
turned out to be so much more.
克萊爾·彼得森 愛荷華州一位郵遞員的兒子
Clair Patterson, son of a letter carrier from Iowa,
天性叛逆 學校表現一般
was rebellious by nature and not very good in school.
但他卻是天生的科學家
But he was a natural born scientist.
一位名叫哈里森·布朗的地質學家
A geologist named Harrison Brown
交給彼得森一項看似簡單的科學作業
gave Patterson what seemed like a straightforward scientific assignment
首先 派特
First off, Pat...
你不介意我叫你派特吧
You mind if I call you Pat?
我知道你不是地質學家
Now, I know you're no geologist...
很可能還分不清長石和花崗岩
probably couldn't tell granite from feldspar...
但我聽說你使用質譜儀很在行
but I hear you really know your way around a mass spectrometer, Pat
很好 結婚了嗎
Good. You married, Pat?
結了 她叫勞瑞 也是研究化學的
Yeah, Laurie. Yeah, she-she's a chemist, too.
我們曾在橡樹嶺一起為曼哈頓計劃工作過
Uh, we worked on the Manhattan Project together,at Oak Ridge
第二次世界大戰期間研發與製造原子彈的一項大型軍事工程
好 很好 首先你要瞭解
Good. Okay, well, first thing you need to know:
這些被稱為鋯石的小晶體
There are these tiny crystals called zircons.
非常小 針尖大小 結構緊密 堅硬
Real small, size of a pinhead, tight as a drum and tough.
穩定性極高
Nothing gets in or out of 'em.
幾十億年如一日
And I'm talking for billions of years.
我們通過對包含它們的岩石年份測定 得知了它們的年份
We know how old these grains are because we've already dated the rocks they came from.
每個鋯石只含有百萬分之幾的鈾
Each little zircon has only a few parts per million
而這些鈾又進一步衰變為
of uranium inside, and that uranium is decaying
更少量的鉛
to even tinier amounts of lead.
只要測量出鉛的含量
Now, you figure out how to measure that lead,
就能知道隕石的年代
and you'll know how to do it for a meteorite.
你能做到嗎
You think you can do that, Pat?
可以 應該沒問題
Yeah. Yeah, I... I don't see why not.
很好 如果你做到了 你就是第一個知道地球年齡的人
Good, because when you do, you'll be the first man to know the age of the earth.
你就出名了
And you'll be famous.
很簡單的
And you'll see: It'll be easy.
易如反掌
Duck soup.
當彼得森在測量鋯石微粒中的微量鉛時
While Patterson tried to measure the trace amounts of lead in the zircon grains
另外一位名叫喬治迪爾頓的研究生
another grad student, George Tilton,
也在測定鋯石中的鈾含量
was measuring the amount of uranium in the same grains.
彼得森只要對鉛含量做等精度測量就可以
All Patterson had to do was measure the amount of lead with equal accuracy
即保持測量條件不變
交給你了 派特
She's all yours, Pat.
測了6次 結果相同
Measured it six times. Same result:
百萬分之3.2
3.2 parts per million.
好的 喬治 謝啦
Yeah, nice going, George, thanks.
迪爾頓的結果每次都是一樣的
Tilton's results were always the same.
但是彼得森測量相同微粒的鉛含量的結果卻差別很大
But Patterson's results on the lead content of the same grains were wildly inconsistent
沒道理啊
This made no sense.
有可能是因為以前含鉛實驗污染了實驗室嗎
Could the lab have been contaminated by previous experiments with lead?
或許是自然界中
Maybe it was the naturally high amounts
高含量的鉛影響了實驗結果
of lead in the environment that were messing up his results.
彼得森用盡了辦法清除實驗室的鉛
Patterson did everything he could to cleanse the lab of any lead
數月後
鉛含量還是超出了100倍
There was still 100 times too much lead.
他已經花費了2年多的時間
He had been at it for more than two years.
易如反掌個鬼啊
Duck soup, my ass.
禁止入內
彼得森意識到他必須用酸來煮容器和工具
Patterson realized he would have to boil his containers and tools in acid
並且提純化學原料 以進一步的降低實驗室中的鉛
and purify all his chemicals to further reduce the lead in his lab
不要啊 噢 我是新來的
Hey, you... Oh, I... No! I'm new here
廁所在哪
Uh, where's the men's room?
見鬼
Ugh damn it.
不論彼得森怎樣擦洗消毒
All of Patterson's obsessive scouring and sterilizing
都沒能夠解決問題
had still not solved the problem.
他必須從頭開始設計建造他自己的實驗室
He would need to design his own lab and build it from scratch.
哈里森布朗轉去位於帕薩迪納的加州理工學院時
The opportunity arose when Harrison Brown moved
機會出現了
to the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena
他邀請彼得森同行
and invited Patterson to join him.
加州理工學院
禁止入內
警告 無菌環境
限制區域 只許實驗人員進入
好了 湯姆 可以了
Okay, Tom, that's enough.
我們現在可以進去了
We can move through the interlock, now.
彼得森在這個項目上已經花費了6年時間
Patterson had now been at it for six years,
堅持不懈的找到並消滅了許多對儀器
doggedly tracking down and eliminating the many sources of lead
造成影響的鉛的源頭
that were compromising his instruments.
他建造了世界上第一個超級潔淨室
He had built the world's first ultra-clean room.
他終於可以測量出岩石中鉛的確切含量
He was finally able to measure how much lead was actually in the rock
岩石的年代已經確定了
One whose age had already been established.
彼得森終於可以利用這塊鐵隕石
Now, at last, Patterson was ready to tackle the iron meteorite
找出地球的年齡
to find the true age of the earth.
他將隕石樣本帶到阿貢國家實驗室
He brought his meteorite specimen back to the Argonne National Laboratory...
在那裏 世界上最精確的質譜儀剛剛投入使用
Where the world's most accurate mass spectrometer had just become operational
博士 就不能等到明天嗎
Doc, this can't wait till tomorrow?
好了 小傢伙 我們要把你氣化了
Okay, little buddy, we're gonna have to vaporize you.
質譜儀利用磁場將樣本中的元素分離
A mass spectrometer uses magnets to separate the elements contained in a sample
從而使得各種元素可以被量化
so that the amounts of each element can be quantified.
這就是解開地球真實年齡之謎的最後一環
This would provide the last missing piece in the puzzle of the earth's true age
現在 我要把你離子化
Now I'm gonna ionize you, yeah.
沒有聽上去那麼可怕
Sounds worse than it is.
小夥伴們很親密呦
What's an electron between friends?
杜絕了樣本被外界的鉛污染後
Having isolated the sample from any outside lead contamination,
彼得森終於可以測量樣本中的鉛和鈾的含量了
Patterson was, at last, ready to measure the amount of lead and uranium in the sample
並且測定它形成的年代了
and calculate how many years before it had formed.
地球的真實年齡
The true age of the earth.
感謝所有做出過貢獻的科學家們
Thank you to all the scientists who came before.
感謝地質學家們
Thank you, geologists.
感謝查爾斯·萊爾
Thank you, Charles Lyell.
著名地質學家 均變說的重要論述者
感謝邁克爾·法拉第
Thank you, Michael Faraday.
發現電磁感應
約瑟夫·湯姆森
J.J. Thomson.
發現電子
歐內斯特·盧瑟福
Ernest Rutherford.
核物理之父
感謝哈里森·布朗
Thank you, Harrison Brown.
研究如何分開鈽和鈾
地球的年齡是45億歲
The world is four and a half billion years old.
我們成功了
We did it.
媽
Mom?
Mom.
彼得森想最先把這個困擾他多年的謎團
Patterson wanted his mother to be the first person
與他的母親分享
to know what he had struggled for so many years to discover
地球的真實年齡
The true age of the earth.
這項發現為他帶來什麼獎勵嗎
His reward for this discovery?
天大的麻煩
A world of trouble.
他當時並不知道
He didn't know it, but he was on a collision course
他妨礙了某些世界上最有權力的人的利益
with some of the most powerful people on the planet.
對於古羅馬人來說
To the ancient Romans,
雄偉的土星並不是一個地點
the majestic ringed planet Saturn was not a real place,
其單詞也有農神的意思
也不是星球 而是天神
not a world, but a God King,
天地結合的結晶
a son of the marriage of heaven and earth,
鉛神
the God of lead.
這些立柱都是羅馬廣場上最古老神廟的遺跡
These columns are all that remain of this oldest temple in the Roman forum
最早是在2500年前供奉農神
first consecrated to Saturn 2,500 years ago.
後來用做羅馬的金庫
It also served as Rome's treasury
也做過計量局
and its bureau of weights and measures.
今天是古羅馬的農神節
Tonight is Saturnalia,
向農神表示敬意的12月狂歡節
the wild december holiday in Saturn's honor.
日常生活行為徹底顛倒
And everyday life will be turned upside down.
主人為奴僕服務
The masters will serve the slaves,
停止一切戰爭和死刑
no wars or executions will be allowed,
人們相互給予禮物
and gifts will be exchanged.
幾百年後
A couple of hundred years from now,
當早年間的牧師們想要吸引更多教徒時
when the early church fathers look for a way to attract more pagans,
他們把農神節變成了聖誕節
they'll decide to turn Saturnalia into Christmas,
給這個冬季的節日賦予了新的意義
making it the latest in a long line of winter solstice holidays to be re-purposed
在農神節的夜晚這個高聳的農神神像看上去好像是這個樣子
This towering statue of Saturn may have look something like this on the night of saturnalia
但是在古羅馬 他還有更陰暗的一面
But in ancient Rome, this God had another, darker side.
農神是一個冷酷的憤懣的行動遲緩的食屍鬼
That other Saturn is a cold and sullen, sluggish ghoul,
動不動就亂發脾氣
given to irrational bouts of rage.
她對他父親的罪行難以言喻
He committed an unspeakable act of violence against his father,
甚至吞噬了自己的孩子
and devoured his own children.
在所有古人能用肉眼看見的行星中
Of all the planets visible to the unaided eyes of the ancients
土星的速度是最慢的
Saturn is the slowest,
這也就是古人用鉛神的名字為他命名的原因
which could explain why it's named after the God of lead
不可否認的是
But there's no denying
農神性格的陰暗面
that the more negative aspects of Saturn's personality
其實反映的是古代人們對於鉛中毒的認識
reflect the age-old knowledge of the symptoms of lead poisoning.
有意思的是
Funny thing about the Romans.
儘管他們知道
Even though they knew
接觸鉛會使人中毒
that contact with lead inevitably poisoned people,
造成不育還有發狂
rendered them sterile and drove them mad,
你猜他們是用的什麼材料
what metal did they use to make the pipes
修建他們大名鼎鼎的供水管道呢
that carried the water through their legendary aqueducts?
給你個提示
I'll give you a hint.
水管這個詞
The word "plumbing" comes
就是來源於拉丁文裏的 鉛
from the Latin word for lead, "plumbum."
他們用什麼金屬製造他們的浴缸呢
What metal did they use to line their famous baths?
如果葡萄酒太酸時他們怎麼辦呢
And how did they sweeten their wines when they were too sour?
他們的鍋碗瓢盆又是什麼材料呢
What did they use to line their vats and cooking pots?
部分歷史學家相信
There are some historians who believe
鉛的廣泛使用是造成
that the widespread use of lead was a major cause
羅馬帝國覆滅的主因
in the decline and fall of the Roman Empire.
為什麼他們在知道鉛有毒後還繼續使用呢
Why did they continue to use lead long after they knew it was toxic?
因為它便宜 延展性好 製造簡單
It was cheap, very malleable, easy to work with,
大量接觸致命劑量的那些人
and the ones who were exposed to it at its most lethal levels...
礦工和處理鉛的工人
the miners and workers who processed the lead...
都是無關緊要的
were considered expendable.
他們的性命不重要
Their lives didn't matter.
他們是奴隸
They were slaves.
地球上大部分的鉛最初都是深埋在地下 與生物保持安全的距離
Most of the earth's lead started off at a safe distance from living things, down below the surface
但是大約8500年前
but about 8,500 years ago,
人們知道了如何從地裏挖東西
humans began figuring out how to dig into the earth
從岩石中提煉金屬
and extract metals from rock.
這個莊園新建成時
By the time this villa was new,
也就幾千年前
just a couple of thousand years ago,
羅馬人年產鉛8萬噸
the romans were producing 80,000 tons of lead a year.
為什麼鉛對我們的危害這麼大
Why is lead so poisonous to us?
因為當鉛進入我們的體內
Because when it gets into our bodies,
鉛假裝成其他金屬 比如鋅或者鐵
lead mimics other metals, like zinc and iron,
細胞茁壯成長確實需要的元素
the ones our cells actually need to grow and flourish.
細胞中的酶被鉛的偽裝迷惑
Enzymes in the cell are fooled by the lead's masquerade,
它們開始結合
and they begin to dance.
這是致命的結合 因為鉛無法滿足
But it's a dance of death, because the lead is an imposter
對細胞至關重要的需要
that can't fulfill the cell's vital needs.
鉛也會妨礙神經轉物質
Lead also blocks neurotransmitters,
堵塞細胞間的交流網絡
the communication network between the cells.
干擾對記憶和學習能力至關重要的分子的神經末梢
It interferes with the molecular receptors that are vital to memory and learning.
對孩童尤為有害
This is especially damaging to children,
沒人可以避免
but lead poisoning spares no one.
從進入20世紀開始
Starting at the turn of the 20th century,
含鉛油漆廠商們僱傭剛萌芽的廣告業者向消費者灌輸
the makers of leaded paint hired the fledgling advertising industry to persuade the consumer
鉛對孩童無害的觀念
that lead was child-friendly.
玩具小鉛兵對荷蘭小孩說
A little toy lead soldier once to the Dutch boy said,
我們好多小夥伴身體裏都有一點點的鉛
"we have some fine relations who all contain some lead."
我們開個派對讓你認識一下偉大的鉛家族中
"Why don't you give a party so folks can meet and see
其他的快樂小夥伴吧
"the other happy members of the great lead family?"
第一個到來的是快樂的電燈泡
The first one at the party was gay electric light.
他說 "我非常亮"
"He said, " I'm very brilliant."
"我在黑夜裏閃閃發光"
"I always shine at night."
"我這麼亮可不是因為我的玻璃頭"
"No little of my brilliance is due to my glass head,"
"讓光線更明亮"
which gives a light much brighter
"其實是因為我是鉛做的"
"because it's made with lead."
一對橡膠進來挽住荷蘭小孩的手臂
A pair or rubbers entered and took the Dutch boy's arm.
他們說 "我們讓你的鞋子保持乾燥和暖和"
They said, " we are protectors who keep you dry and warm.
"製造我們的人說"
"You knew when we were molded, the man who made us said,"
"我們堅固耐用還很活潑"
we're strong and tough and lively
"這是因為我們含有鉛"
"because in us, there's lead."
那時含鉛產品還沒有真正開始大發展
But lead production didn't really shift into high gear
直到20年代早期
until the early 1920's
化學狂人托馬斯·米基利夥同投資人
when chemist Thomas Midgley and inventor.
他也是氟利昂的發明人
通用汽車的查爾斯·凱特靈
Charles Kettering of General Motors
將四乙基鉛以抗爆劑為噱頭添加到汽油中
found that tetraethyl lead could be marketed as an anti-knock additive to gasoline.
四乙基鉛在那時用於提高汽油的辛烷值
他們成立了乙基公司
They formed a new company called the Ethyl Corporation.
美國陸軍部曾經考慮用它做毒氣
It had once been considered for use as a poison gas by the U.S. war department
和油漆中的鉛不同 四乙基鉛是脂溶性的
Unlike the lead in paint, tetraethyl lead was fat soluble.
皮膚接觸半杯的量就會致命
A half a cup of it on your skin could kill you.
生產廠家統計銷量可以達到每年6千萬噸
The manufacturers calculated that they could sell 60 million tons of it a year
只有一個問題
Only problem was,
一些在特拉華州和新澤西州工廠工作的員工
some of the workers who processed the stuff
變得精神失常 出現幻覺
in factories in Delaware and New Jersey were going insane, hallucinating,
跳窗而出
jumping out of windows.
死狀恐怖
They died screaming.
這時銷售宣傳需要的就不僅僅是會跳舞的燈泡了
This was a selling job that would require a lot more than dancing light bulbs
他們需要一個懂科學的人
What was needed was a man of science
安撫民眾的恐慌 並且提升鉛的形象
to calm the public's fears and improve lead's image.
他們找到了一個合適的人選
They found the right man for the job.
那也是第一次
This was one of the first times
利用科學權威來遮掩對環境和公共健康的威脅
that the authority of science was used to cloak a threat to public health and the environment
辛辛那提的一位年輕博士 羅伯特基歐
Robert Kehoe, a young doctor from Cincinnati,
受雇於通用汽車
was hired by GM.
他對公眾擔心的鉛的危害提出了反駁
He raised scientific doubts in the public mind about the dangers of lead
他說 鉛是環境中天然存在的
Lead was naturally occurring in the environment, he said.
確實可能對第一線的工人造成職業傷害 但是
Yes, there might be occupational hazards for the people who worked with lead, but
業界自我監管就夠了
that could be best handled by industry self-regulation.
並沒有證據表明
And there was no evidence to suggest
鉛會對消費者構成威脅
that lead posed any threat to the consumer.
幾十年來 沒有人反駁他
For decades no one challenged him...
直到克萊爾·彼得森開始研究
Until Clair Patterson went searching
地球的年齡
for the age of the earth.
克萊爾·彼得森對地球年齡的研究
Claire Patterson's research on the age of the earth
使他成為世界上測量痕量鉛領域首屈一指的專家
had made him the world's leading expert on measuring trace amounts of lead
和當時的其他人一樣
And like everyone else at the time,
他猜想鉛是天然普遍存在的
he assumed the prevalence of lead occurred naturally.
像他這樣真正的科學家
True scientist that he was, he set out
他開始盡全力探究鉛是如何在環境中傳播的
to discover everything he could about how lead circulates through the environment.
依靠美國石油組織的撥款
On a grant from the American Petroleum Institute,
他仔細的測量了深層和淺層海水中的鉛濃度
he carefully measured the concentrations of lead in deep and shallow seawater
彼得森又一次發現他的原始數據無法解釋了
Once again, Patterson found that his initial data made no sense.
深層海水中只有極少量的鉛濃度
There were only minuscule concentrations of lead in the deep ocean water
但在淺水和水面上
But in shallow waters and at the surface,
鉛濃度卻要高出幾百倍
the concentrations of lead were hundreds of times greater.
海洋中 要用幾百年淺層海水才會與深層海水相混合
In any ocean, it takes a few hundred years for the shallow waters to mix with the deep.
彼得森得出結論 表層海水中大量的鉛是最近才出現的
This told Patterson that the large amount of lead in the surface waters had arrived recently.
否則它會分佈的更均勻
Otherwise it would have been more evenly distributed.
知道了淺層的鉛濃度以及與深層混合所需要的時間
Knowing the quantity of lead in the shallow seas and the time needed to mix it into the deeper layers
他就可以估算出表面的鉛污染比率
he was able to estimate the rate of lead contamination at the surface.
彼得森問自己
Patterson asked himself
是什麼能給全球的海洋帶來這麼多的鉛
what could possibly supply lead to the world's oceans at such a rate.
這些鉛都是哪裏來的
Where's all that lead coming from?
我知道了 哈里森
I think I know, Harrison.
它來自含鉛汽油
It's from leaded gasoline.
好吧 這個有點麻煩 派特
Well, then we've got a problem, Pat,
因為我們的資金都是從那裏來的
because that's the same place the money comes from.
但是彼得森沒有屈服
But Patterson would not give in.
他立即著手發表學術論文
He went right to work on publishing the scientific paper
對含鉛汽油做出討伐
that would make the case against leaded gasoline.
他把論文寄給了久負盛名的科學期刊
When he sent the paper to the prestigious scientific journal
《自然》 彼得森將自己的名字放在後面
Nature, Patterson put his own name second.
他過去常常這樣 幫助他的學生提高聲望
He often did that with his students to advance their reputations
他一輩子都在避免出風頭以及迴避隨之而來的好處
He made a lifelong point of shunning the limelight and the privileges that come with it
發表後僅3天
Only three days after publication...
反擊開始了
the push-back began.
-你好 彼得森博士 -很高興見到你
- Hello, Dr. Patterson. - Pleasure to meet you.
您的研究成果很了不起
Very impressed by your work.
您的研究成果對我們石油化工行業有很大的影響
Your work is of great interest to us in the petroleum and chemical industries
多虧了你們的贊助
Well, it wouldn't have been possible without your funding.
沒錯 我們還希望提供給你更多的幫助
Precisely. And there's so much more we'd like to do for you.
正好 我還想在極地冰層中測量鉛含量
Well, I've been thinking about measuring lead in polar ice
看看是不是和海洋中的結果一樣
to see if it shows the same kind of pattern as the oceans.
鉛 你的工作已經結束了
Lead? But you've already done that.
是時候研究其他微量元素了
We're thinking it's time you move on to other trace elements.
其實 彼得森博士
In fact, Dr. Patterson,
我們有能力資助你去無限制地研究其他方面
our ability to fund you in any other line of research is...Virtually limitless.
鉛是一種神經毒素
Lead is a neurotoxin.
你們將四乙基鉛從工廠運出來時
When you ship your tetraethyl lead from the factory...
在加進汽油之前
before you add it to the gasoline...
就像是運送化學武器
it's handled just like a chemical weapon.
都是有原因的
There's a reason for that.
你們覺得這些鉛從排氣管中排出後都去了哪裏呢
Where do you suppose all that lead goes after it leaves the tailpipe
想想這會對我們和我們的後代造成什麼影響
Think about what it might be doing to us and our kids.
基歐博士已經證明了這種程度的鉛
Dr. Kehoe has shown that the level of lead in the environment
在環境中就如同12月的雪一樣自然
...is as natural as snow in December
那它怎麼會在深層海水中存在呢
Then why doesn't it show up in the deep water? Here,
我給你看
let me just show you.
多謝了
Thanks for your time.
等等 你們還要把上百萬噸的毒氣排到我們呼吸的空氣中嗎
Wait, you're just gonna keep on putting millions of tons of poison into the air we breathe?
就算我的研究不能使你們停產 以後也有科學家可以做到
If my research doesn't put you out of business some future scientist will
石油行業來的贊助一夜之間消失得無影無蹤
Patterson's funding from the oil industry vanished overnight
事實上 他們要讓他失業
In fact, they tried to get him fired.
但是美國政府 陸軍 海軍
But the U.S. government... The Army, the Navy,
原子能委員會 公共衛生署
the atomic energy commission, the public health service,
還有國家科學基金會 都支持他
and the National Science Foundation... Stood by him,
支持他的鉛污染研究
supporting his research on lead pollution.
為了調查研究 從最北的格陵蘭到最南的大西洋都有他的足跡
His investigations took him from Greenland in the far north to Antarctica in the far south
足跡遍佈各個河流與山川
and to rivers, mountains and valleys in between.
即使面對最惡劣的條件
In even the most hostile conditions,
彼得森和他的團隊協力複製了
Patterson and his team worked to replicate
無塵室的無污染環境
the immaculate environment of the clean room.
他們每天都更換塑料制服
Their plastic suits were replaced daily.
在零下溫度下中工作10-12個小時
Working ten-to 12-hour days in subzero weather,
他們在南極洲冰層中鑽了深達200英尺的通道
they dug a 200-foot-long shaft into the ice of Antarctica
約為61米
那是某種程度上的時間旅行
It was a form of time travel,
取得了那是在工業革命開始前
to recover snow that had fallen three centuries ago,
300年前的雪樣
before the start of the Industrial Revolution.
你的鼻子
Nose!
快擦鼻子
Wipe your nose, damn it!
你體內的鉛比冰裏的高1千倍
There's a thousand times more lead in you than in this ice!
你這是想要污染整個樣本嗎
You want to contaminate the whole damn sample?!
經過4個星期的精疲力盡的艱苦樣本採集工作後
After four grueling weeks of painstaking sample collection
彼得森準備回到實驗室了
Patterson was ready to go back to the lab.
和海水中一樣 他發現在雪中
As with the oceans, he found that the amount of lead
幾百年前的鉛含量要低得多
was much lower in the snow of a few hundred years before.
不論在地球上的其他什麼地方
No matter where he searched on earth,
也不管多久以前的樣本
no matter how far he traveled back in time,
結果都說明一件事
the results always told the same story:
過去空氣和水中天然存在的含量要低得多得多
The naturally occurring levels in the air and water in the past, were far lower.
幾千年來 人們都知道
For thousands of years, lead had been known
鉛會造成腦損傷 影響發育
to cause brain damage, developmental impairment,
暴力行為 甚至致命
violent behavior, and even death.
在地球年齡的研究中
In searching for the age of the earth,
彼得森無意中發現了一場空前規模的毒害污染的證據
Patterson had stumbled on the evidence for a mass poisoning on an unprecedented scale.
但是基歐和其他受雇於鉛工業的科學家
But Kehoe and the other scientists employed by the lead industry
勸說民眾無需為此擔心
persuaded the public they had nothing to worry about.
所有人都認為彼得森是個騙子
Everyone thought Patterson was a crank
直到有個人開始關注這個問題
Until one man started to pay attention.
彼得森將他的發現公佈於眾
Patterson went public with his discoveries about lead in a big way
他把研究結果發表在主要的環境健康期刊上
He published his findings in a major environmental health journal
也寄給了多位政府高層
and sent copies to various government leaders,
包括一位很有影響力的參議員
including one highly influential senator.
緬因州參議員埃德蒙·馬斯基
Edmund Muskie of Maine
是時任的參議院大氣與水污染委員會主席
was the chairman of the senate subcommittee on air and water pollution
1966年他主持了關於鉛問題的聽證會
In 1966 he held hearings on the lead question.
第一位證人
The first witness
羅伯特基歐 含鉛汽油長期以來的支持者
was Dr. Robert Kehoe, longtime scientific advocate for leaded gasoline
你的結論是不是 從1937年到現在
Is it, uh, your conclusion that, in 1937 to the present time, there has been
普通駕駛者和交警
no increase in the amount of lead
還有加油站工作人員從大氣中吸入的
taken in from the atmosphere by the average traffic policeman,
鉛的數量沒有增加
service station attendant, or... Or motorist?
根本沒有證據
There is not the slightest evidence
可以證明這段時間內
that there has been a change in this picture
有任何改變
during this period of time.
完全沒有
Not the slightest.
聽證會召開的時間
The hearings were scheduled to take place,
特地選在彼得森在南極洲的時間
when the fiercest critic, Claire Patterson was off in Antarctica.
但是他出人意料地
But he unexpectedly appeared
在第五天出席了
on the fifth day of testimony.
看上去好像人體中鉛濃度的增加
Uh, looks like there seems to be an increase in the concentration of lead in people
是與環境接觸的結果
as a result of exposure to the environment.
是這樣嗎
Is that correct?
是的
That is correct.
至於鑒定典型性德鉛含量
In identifying typical lead levels,
你用的是實地採集的測量結果嗎
you use actual measurements you've taken in the field?
是的
Yes.
這些檢測結果
Are these observations different
與其他證人提出的有區別嗎
from the ones we've been hearing about from other witnesses?
沒有 結果是相同的
No, th... They're the same observations.
你 你的證詞是說
You... You've testified that there has been
自然鉛含量沒有變化 是這樣嗎
no change in natural lead levels, is that correct?
是的
That is correct.
你確定嗎
You're sure about that?
非常肯定
Absolutely.
現在人體中的含量看似很尋常
The levels we see in people today may be typical.
但絕不代表它們是天然的
But they are not by any means natural.
你認同基歐博士的數據嗎
So you don't disagree with Dr. Kehoe's numbers?
認同
Uh, no, no.
你是說 根據相同的數據
You're saying that the same numbers
得出了不同的結論
are leading to different conclusions?
是的
Yes.
這種話 通常是
You know, this is the kind of thing
律師說的 不是科學家
we expect to hear from lawyers, not scientists.
我也是這麼認為
I would agree with that, yes.
基歐博士 你好像對你的結論很有把握
You seem to be very sure of your conclusions, Dr. Kehoe.
因為我是目前在這個領域最有經驗的
It so happens that I have more experience in this field than anyone else alive
這種含量的鉛對人體有嚴重的長期傷害
At these levels, lead is a severe chronic insult to the human body
沒有醫學證據顯示 鉛會危害公眾健康
There is no medical evidence that lead has introduced a danger to public health.
挖掘幾百萬噸有毒物質並將其
It's irresponsible to mine millions of tons
散佈到環境中 是極其不負責任的
of toxic material and disperse it into the environment!
如果真的有證據 我們早就會發現了
If there was proof of harm, we would have found it.
你們以鉛牟利 當然不會將真實結果公諸於世
Not if your purpose is to sell lead.
彼得森與整個行業又抗爭了20年
Patterson fought the industry for another 20 years
鉛才被禁止在美國消費品中使用
before lead was finally banned in U.S. consumer products.
這位找出地球年齡的人
The man who figured out the age of the earth
同樣也造就了20世紀
was also responsible for one
最偉大的公眾健康問題的勝利
of the greatest public health victories of the 20th century.
短短幾年間 兒童平均
In just a few years, average lead levels
血液鉛含量猛降百分之75
in the blood of children plummeted by some 75%.
如今 醫學界的共識是
Today, the medical consensus is unanimous...
人體內的鉛含量不是無毒 只是量很少而已
there's no such thing as a nontoxic level of lead in humans, however small
現在 科學家又發出了其他環境問題的警告
Today, scientists sound the alarm on other environmental dangers
既得利益團體依然僱傭他們自己的科學家以混淆視聽
Vested interests still hire their own scientists to confuse the issue.
但是到頭來
But in the end,
最終的受害者 又是誰呢
nature will not be fooled.
中文翻譯：@SaltyEggPain timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息